Alexander Biba

Senior Software Engineer

Contact

≥ alexbiba@gmail.com



P Jersey City, NJ, 07302

Expert Skills

- JavaScript
- Python
- Linux
- SQL
- Groovy

Advanced Skills

- Vue.js
- React.js
- Node.js
- C/C++
- Java

Languages

English - Fluent Hebrew - Native

Russian - Basic

Personal

During my spare time I enjoy video games, guitar playing, exploring nature and the big city.

Personal Statement

Senior Software Engineer with more than five years of experience in backend and full-stack application development. Coming from a backend oriented background, I enjoy developing frontend applications and now looking for a full-stack engineering role with strong emphasis on backend development.

Education

Technion, Israel, B.Sc. Computer Engineering 02/2011 - 04/2017

Experience

Bloomberg NY: Full-Stack Engineer in Equity Research

10/2018 - 05/2022

Developed Equity Research Discoverability products that expose users to a wide range of company-related documents: a *Document Search Engine* (JS, Python, SQL, C++) and a *Collaborative Document Viewer* Web Application (Vue.js, Node.js, Groovy, Java, Python, SQL). Some of my projects included:

- Facilitating a Websocket infrastructure throughout our application which greatly improved collaboration on our platform by allowing users to add comments and annotations, that would propagate to other users' document viewers in real time.
- Rewriting our document text-search library, which included:
 - Reducing the code from hundreds of lines to a little over 100
 - Removing complicated regular-expressions
 - Using peg.js grammar to generate parsers
 - Adding unit tests to ensure stability and backwards-compatibility

Bloomberg Tel-Aviv: Software Engineer in BTCA

09/2016 - 10/2018

Developed *Bloomberg's Transaction Cost Analysis* application running on the Bloomberg Terminal (JavaScript, Python, C++, SQL). Some of my projects included:

- Implementing an audit system on every user action across our application, which allowed user admins to track user actions in their firm. This required backend Python work, as well as frontend JS.
- Integrating IBM Cognos report generation software into our system to provide users with better data visualization by writing a Python XML SAX parser to transform our data and using RabbitMQ to throttle inputs.

Personal Projects

Goal Keeper

github.com/AlexanderBiba/goal-keeper

A task manager that allows users to designate a reviewer for their daily tasks, written in React.js with Material UI, and Firebase DB.

More projects available on GitHub github.com/AlexanderBiba